<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Galaxies on Brian Koberlein</title>
    <link>/tags/galaxies/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Galaxies on Brian Koberlein</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <copyright>CC BY-NC 4.0</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 31 Mar 2018 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
        <atom:link href="/tags/galaxies/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>What&#39;s in a Name?</title>
      <link>/whats-name/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 31 Mar 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/whats-name/</guid>
      <description><figure class="featured">
      <img src="/image/sombrerogalaxy.jpg" alt="" />
      <figcaption><p>The Sombrero Galaxy looks a bit like a sombrero. Credit: NASA/ESA and The Hubble Heritage Team (STScI/AURA)</p></figcaption>
    </figure>&lt;p&gt;Yesterday I wrote about a &lt;a href=&#34;https://blog.briankoberlein.com/out-dark&#34;&gt;galaxy containing almost no dark matter&lt;/a&gt;. I didn&amp;rsquo;t mention its name, but it happens to be NGC1052-DF2. Of all the possible names you could give a galaxy, why that one? It all has to do with the history of how the galaxy was discovered.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some galaxies have wonderful names: Andromeda, Triangulum, and the Milky Way. Others are commonly known by a descriptive name, such as the Sombrero Galaxy with its distinctive rim of dust, or the Tadpole Galaxy with it&amp;rsquo;s long trail of stars. Others are named after its discover, such as Mayall&amp;rsquo;s Object, or Hoag&amp;rsquo;s Object. But there are billions of known galaxies in the heavens, so most, such as NGC1052-DF2, are known by a catalog name.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The history of galaxy catalogs has its origin with &lt;a href=&#34;https://briankoberlein.com/2014/11/18/act-frustration/&#34;&gt;Charles Messier&lt;/a&gt;. In the 1700s, Messier was looking for comets, which look like faint nebulous blurs before they become brighter and grow long tails. Other objects known as nebulae also look like faint blurs. To keep from confusing the two, Messier created a list of nebulae. That way when he found a faint blur he could compare it with his nebula catalogue to see if it really was a comet. This became known as the Messier Catalog, and contains 110 objects. Each object is denoted by an M for Messier, and then it&amp;rsquo;s catalog number. So the Andromeda Galaxy is known as M31. Not all of Messier&amp;rsquo;s objects are galaxies. Telescopes at the time weren&amp;rsquo;t powerful enough to distinguish between galaxies and other objects such as globular clusters and planetary nebulae. But 40 of the Messier objects are galaxies, making them the first galaxy catalog.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 1864, John Herschel published the &lt;em&gt;General Catalogue of Nebulae and Clusters of Stars&lt;/em&gt;, containing 5,079 objects. It expanded on the earlier work of his father William Herschel. This was expanded to 7,840 objects in 1888 by John Dreyer, and became known as the New General Catalogue, or NGC. The New General Catalogue was revised in 1973 and 1988, and is the most comprehensive list of nearby (in cosmic terms) galaxies. This is why galaxies often have the name NGC followed by a number.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But our particular galaxy has a hypened addition, and that&amp;rsquo;s because it isn&amp;rsquo;t in the main catalogue. It is a companion galaxy to NGC1052. Lots of the NGC galaxies have smaller companions, just as the Large and Small Magellanic clouds are companion galaxies to our own Milky Way. Since the galaxy was discovered by a telescope known as the Dragonfly Telephoto Array, and it was the second companion galaxy to be found, our galaxy has the name NGC1052-DF2.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Catalogs are a powerful tool of astronomers. They help us keep track of objects in the sky, and make sure different objects don&amp;rsquo;t get confused with each other. The only real downside is that they lead to some rather cumbersome names.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Out of the Dark</title>
      <link>/out-dark/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 30 Mar 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/out-dark/</guid>
      <description><figure class="featured">
      <img src="/image/cluster.jpg" alt="" />
      <figcaption><p>A galaxy without dark matter. Credit: Image credit: Gemini Observatory/NSF/AURA/Keck/Jen Miller/Joy Pollard</p></figcaption>
    </figure>&lt;p&gt;Dark matter is the &lt;a href=&#34;https://briankoberlein.com/2014/08/15/five-facts/&#34;&gt;mystery&lt;/a&gt; that holds the universe together. Although it can&amp;rsquo;t be seen directly, we know it is there through its gravitational effect on light and the motion of matter. Dark matter makes up most of a galaxy&amp;rsquo;s mass, and there are some galaxies that are &lt;a href=&#34;https://briankoberlein.com/2016/09/02/dark-galaxy/&#34;&gt;almost entirely dark matter&lt;/a&gt;. This makes sense, because the atoms and molecules of stars and dust comprise only 12% of the mass in the universe. In the standard cosmological model, clumps of dark matter triggered the formation of galaxies and galactic clusters in the early universe, where there are galaxies there is dark matter. But recently astronomers have found a galaxy with almost no dark matter, and it&amp;rsquo;s raising questions about how it could have formed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The galaxy in question is an &lt;a href=&#34;https://briankoberlein.com/2017/09/03/puzzle-fluffy-galaxies/&#34;&gt;ultradiffuse galaxy&lt;/a&gt;. These are galaxies that can be as big as our Milky Way, but contain only a few billion stars, rather than the 400 billion of our home galaxy. Because they are diffuse and faint we have only recently been able to study them. Most of these ultradiffuse galaxies contain dark matter, but this new galaxy is different.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The amount of dark matter in a galaxy can be estimated by studying the &lt;a href=&#34;https://briankoberlein.com/2015/06/09/amassing-evidence/&#34;&gt;motion of globular clusters&lt;/a&gt; in a galaxy. These are tight clusters of stars that are scattered around a galaxy like a halo. The more mass a galaxy has, the faster these clusters move as they orbit the galaxy. By comparing the speed of globular clusters with the brightness of stars in a galaxy, we can compare the visible mass of a galaxy to its total mass. When the team did this for the new galaxy, they found the motion of its globular clusters agreed with the visible mass of stars and dust. No dark matter is needed to make up the difference.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The existence of a galaxy free from dark matter further confirms that dark matter is both real and different from regular matter. If dark matter were an illusion due to &lt;a href=&#34;https://briankoberlein.com/2014/08/16/old-model-doesnt-work/&#34;&gt;modified gravity&lt;/a&gt; then such a galaxy couldn&amp;rsquo;t exist. Dark matter is out there, just not in this particular galaxy. But if that&amp;rsquo;s true, then how could this galaxy have formed. One idea is that the galaxy could have been involved in a collision with another galaxy, which stripped away its dark matter. But a survey of the surrounding area shows no evidence of a collision.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The only way to solve this mystery is to look for other dark-matter free galaxies. Until then we&amp;rsquo;re not yet out of the dark.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Wheel of Time</title>
      <link>/wheel-time/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 15 Mar 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/wheel-time/</guid>
      <description><figure class="featured">
      <img src="/image/pinwheelgalaxy.jpg" alt="" />
      <figcaption><p>The beautiful Pinwheel Galaxy. Credit: Hubble/Suburu</p></figcaption>
    </figure>&lt;p&gt;The universe moves like clockwork. Their motions can be described by elegant gravitational equations, which trace the motions of everything from planets to galaxies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The gravitational attraction between any two bodies is stronger when they are closer together, a property known as the &lt;a href=&#34;https://briankoberlein.com/2014/03/27/mutual-attraction-2/&#34;&gt;inverse square law&lt;/a&gt;. As a result, objects orbit each other more quickly when they are close together. The planet &lt;a href=&#34;https://briankoberlein.com/2014/03/21/icy-hot/&#34;&gt;Mercury&lt;/a&gt; orbits the Sun once every 88 days, while distant &lt;a href=&#34;https://briankoberlein.com/2014/04/04/neptune-night/&#34;&gt;Neptune&lt;/a&gt; takes 165 years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Galaxies don&amp;rsquo;t follow this relation. Most of the visible matter in a galaxy is concentrated at its center, just like our solar system. So you would expect that stars close to the center of a galaxy would move much more quickly than those on the outer edge. But it turns out that both central and edge stars move at about the same speed. This is due to the fact that galaxies are largely comprised of &lt;a href=&#34;https://briankoberlein.com/2014/08/15/five-facts/&#34;&gt;dark matter&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure class=&#34;right&#34;&gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;/image/rotationrelation.png&#34; alt=&#34;The relation between rotation speed and galaxy size.&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;
        The relation between rotation speed and galaxy size.
        
            
        
        &lt;/p&gt; 
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Even with dark matter, galaxies vary widely in mass. So one would still expect stars in dense and massive galaxies to orbit more quickly than stars in more diffuse galaxies. But it turns out that isn&amp;rsquo;t the case.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; New observations of galaxies found that regardless of a galaxy&amp;rsquo;s size, the stars on the outer edge of the galaxy take about a billion years to orbit the galaxy once. The relation holds for small dwarf galaxies just as well as it holds for massive spiral galaxies. We aren&amp;rsquo;t entirely sure why. Some simple models of galactic evolution allow for such a relation, but we will need more data to pin down the exact mechanism.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This isn&amp;rsquo;t the first time we&amp;rsquo;ve found a relation among galaxies without fully understanding the underlying cause. The most famous one is the &lt;a href=&#34;https://briankoberlein.com/2013/11/17/tully-fisher-king/&#34;&gt;Tully-Fisher relation&lt;/a&gt;, which connects rotation speed to the overall brightness of a galaxy. But even without a known mechanism, this relation could be quite useful. By measuring the speed of stars on the edge of a galaxy, we can easily pin down its overall size. This can be difficult to do with distant galaxies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;footnotes&#34;&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:1&#34;&gt;Meurer, Gerhardt R., et al. &amp;ldquo;Cosmic clocks: a tight radius–velocity relationship for H i-selected galaxies.&amp;rdquo; Monthly Notices of the Royal Astronomical Society 476.2 (2018): 1624-1636. DOI: &lt;a href=&#34;https://arxiv.org/abs/1803.04716&#34;&gt;10.1093/mnras/sty275&lt;/a&gt;
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:1&#34;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>