<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Brian Koberlein</title>
    <link>/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Brian Koberlein</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <copyright>CC BY-NC 4.0</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 18 Apr 2018 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
        <atom:link href="/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Speaker for the Dead</title>
      <link>/speaker-for-the-dead/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 18 Apr 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/speaker-for-the-dead/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Perhaps the most profound question we can hope to answer is whether we are alone in the universe. The vast cosmos is scattered with countless solar systems, and many of these have at least the potential for life. It is quite possible that the universe is teeming with a wondrous variety of exotic life and alien civilizations. It is also possible that life is so rare that Earth alone is life&amp;rsquo;s home.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But what are the odds one way or the other? In 1961 Frank Drake proposed an equation to find out. Drake intended it as a way to frame discussion on the topic, but it came to be known as the &lt;a href=&#34;https://briankoberlein.com/2014/03/15/forever-alone/&#34;&gt;Drake Equation&lt;/a&gt;. The equation itself is basically a product of the rate at which stars form in our galaxy, how many stars have planets, how many planets they typically have, what fraction are habitable, what fraction of habitable planets form life, how many form intelligent life, then civilizations, and how long those civilizations last. If you know all of those values, you can calculate the number of civilizations currently living in our galaxy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 1961 most of the parameters could only be guessed at. We didn&amp;rsquo;t know, for example, whether other stars had planets, since not a single exoplanet had yet been discovered. But we now know that planets are common, and there are somewhere between 8 and 20 billion potentially habitable planets in our galaxy. As a result, there&amp;rsquo;s been renewed interest in searching for signals from alien civilizations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Suppose we were to discover such a signal. Suppose a radio telescope starts to detect an unmistakable message from a distant star. &amp;ldquo;Hello! We are where! Message back if you get this!&amp;rdquo; Even the simplest message would revolutionize our understanding of life in the universe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the space between stars is vast, and light takes thousands of years to travel between them. In the time it takes an alien message to reach us, they may have been destroyed by a plague, a meteor impact. In their folly they might destory themselves through war or environmental devastation. The message we receive could be the last cosmic breath of a dead civilization.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Recently a team &lt;a href=&#34;https://arxiv.org/abs/1802.09399&#34;&gt;looked at this very question&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; If we discover an alien civilization, what are the odds that they are dead. Like Drake&amp;rsquo;s original equation, their model is rather simple, and intended to foster discussion.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure class=&#34;right&#34;&gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;/image/signalshells.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;The expanding signals of dead civilizations cover the most area. Credit: Grimaldi, et al.&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;
        The expanding signals of dead civilizations cover the most area. Credit: Grimaldi, et al.
        
            
        
        &lt;/p&gt; 
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The basic premise is that civilizations survive for a certain period of time, and while they survive they emit signals that could be detected by other civilizations. For example, human civilization has been around for about 12,000 years, but we&amp;rsquo;ve only been able to send radio signals into space for about a century. Those signals travel into space in all directions, so there is an &lt;a href=&#34;https://briankoberlein.com/2015/02/19/e-t-phone-home/&#34;&gt;expanding sphere of signals&lt;/a&gt; from Earth about 100 light years in radius. In the unlikely event that our civilization ends this year, our radio signals would continue to spread outward in a spherical shell 100 light years thick.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If there are lots of civilizations in our galaxy, the expanding envelope of their signals would spread throughout the galaxy, eventually overlapping in places. The team then calculated the odds of detecting a signal from a still living civilization vs a dead one. They found that it depends on how long civilizations typically survive. If the age is typically more than 100,000 years, then we are more likely to detect a message from a living civilization. If the lifetime of a civilization is less than that, any message we receive is likely to be from a dead world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have only been sending signals into space for a century. Do you think our civilization will survive for the next 100 centuries. Will humans still exist in the year 102,018? Or will we perish, leaving only the echoes of our once thriving species. Echoes of a species that arose from the dust for a cosmic moment, but while they lived saw only a lonely night.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;footnotes&#34;&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:1&#34;&gt;Grimaldi, Claudio, Geoffrey W. Marcy, Nathaniel K. Tellis, and Frank Drake. &amp;ldquo;Area Coverage of Expanding ET Signals in the Galaxy: SETI and Drake’s N.&amp;rdquo; Publications of the Astronomical Society of the Pacific 130, no. 987 (2018): 054101.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:1&#34;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Incredible Shrinking Sun</title>
      <link>/incredible-shrinking-sun/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 16 Apr 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/incredible-shrinking-sun/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Our Sun has provided Earth with light for billions of years. This light has allowed life to evolve and flourish on our small planet, but it comes at a cost.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Sun&amp;rsquo;s light is produced by &lt;a href=&#34;https://briankoberlein.com/2014/06/10/chain-reaction/&#34;&gt;fusion in the Sun&amp;rsquo;s core&lt;/a&gt;. Hydrogen atoms combine to produce helium and light. The light is produced because the mass of a helium atom is slightly smaller than the mass of the four hydrogen atoms that formed it. As Einstein first pointed out, &lt;a href=&#34;https://briankoberlein.com/2014/03/26/muse-fire/&#34;&gt;mass and energy can transform into each other&lt;/a&gt;, so the loss of mass means a gain of energy in the form of light. The light radiates from the Sun, warming our Earth, but that also means over time the Sun loses mass. The Sun consumes mass to produce light.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As the Sun loses mass its gravitational pull on the planets weakens slightly. The Sun can&amp;rsquo;t hold the planets as strongly as it used to, so the planets drift a bit further away from the Sun. At least that&amp;rsquo;s the theory. The shift of the planets is so small that it&amp;rsquo;s difficult to measure. There have been some studies that &lt;a href=&#34;https://briankoberlein.com/2016/01/01/relative-units/&#34;&gt;seemed to see the effect with Earth&lt;/a&gt;, but the result isn&amp;rsquo;t particularly strong. The usual method of determining planetary distance is to &lt;a href=&#34;https://briankoberlein.com/2015/11/13/casting-radio-shadows-to-map-the-moon-and-venus/&#34;&gt;bounce radio signals off them&lt;/a&gt;, and it&amp;rsquo;s difficult to do it precisely enough to determine the Sun&amp;rsquo;s changing mass.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is a much better way to measure the position of planets. Simply put a spacecraft in orbit around it. When the Cassini spacecraft was placed in orbit around Saturn, astronomers used radio signals from Cassini to measure the position of Saturn &lt;a href=&#34;https://briankoberlein.com/2015/01/13/last-mile/&#34;&gt;accurate to within a mile&lt;/a&gt;. We can do this because we know exactly what signal comes from the spacecraft, so any shift in that signal tells us how the spacecraft moves. When the Messenger spacecraft was placed in orbit, astronomers used the same technique to measure the position of Mercury. Using seven years of data they could also determine how Mercury&amp;rsquo;s motion changed over time. They did it precisely enough to observe the weakening of the Sun&amp;rsquo;s gravitational tug.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; They found that the Sun&amp;rsquo;s pull is weakening by about 0.4 trillionths of a percent per year. That agrees with estimates of the Sun&amp;rsquo;s mass loss due to core fusion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mercury has long been used as a test of Einstein&amp;rsquo;s theories. It&amp;rsquo;s motion was the &lt;a href=&#34;https://briankoberlein.com/2014/05/19/einstein-eddington/&#34;&gt;first confirmation&lt;/a&gt; that Einstein&amp;rsquo;s theory of gravity could be correct. It&amp;rsquo;s only fitting that Mercury has now be used to confirm &lt;a href=&#34;https://briankoberlein.com/2015/05/08/heart-of-the-matter/&#34;&gt;Einstein&amp;rsquo;s most famous equation&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;footnotes&#34;&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:1&#34;&gt;Genova, Antonio, et al. &amp;ldquo;Solar system expansion and strong equivalence principle as seen by the NASA MESSENGER mission.&amp;rdquo; Nature communications 9.1 (2018): 289. doi:&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.nature.com/articles/s41467-017-02558-1&#34;&gt;10.1038/s41467-017-02558-1&lt;/a&gt;
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:1&#34;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Follow My Lead</title>
      <link>/follow-my-lead/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Apr 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/follow-my-lead/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Yesterday a gentleman posted a comment on an article I wrote about the &lt;a href=&#34;https://briankoberlein.com/2015/08/11/does-the-aether-exist-hint-no/&#34;&gt;luminiferous aether&lt;/a&gt;. For those who aren&amp;rsquo;t familiar, the aether was an idea proposed in the 1800s to explain how light can travel through empty space. Several experiments trying to observe the aether were performed in the late 1800s, but weren&amp;rsquo;t successful. This led Einstein to propose the theory of special relativity. Thus, the aether doesn&amp;rsquo;t exist and the rest is history.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But this gentleman doesn&amp;rsquo;t believe in relativity. He thinks the Earth is stationary and at the center of creation. He proceeded to tell me so, and cited a paper from Nature&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; that he claimed proved Einstein is wrong, and the aether exists.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nature is a fairly impressive journal, so a controversial article on relativity is worth checking out. The gentleman didn&amp;rsquo;t give a proper citation, just &amp;ldquo;Nature Magazine August volume 322,&amp;rdquo; but it was a start. A quick internet search found dozens of websites citing the same article, all arguing the Earth doesn&amp;rsquo;t move, and all citing this article as evidence. A bit more searching and I found a &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.nature.com/articles/322590b0.pdf&#34;&gt;copy of the article&lt;/a&gt;. Well, kind of.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It turns out it isn&amp;rsquo;t an article. It&amp;rsquo;s a one column letter to the editor by one E. W. Silvertooth claiming he did an experiment with details to follow. No evidence, no link, no peer review, just an unsubstantiated claim. Still, supporters of a fixed Earth model cite this article a great deal, refering to it as the Silvertooth experiment. What they don&amp;rsquo;t tend to do is cite any actual experiment.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure class=&#34;center&#34;&gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;/image/silvertooth.png&#34; alt=&#34;A diagram recreating the Silvertooth experiment. Credit: Doug Marett&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;
        A diagram recreating the Silvertooth experiment. Credit: Doug Marett
        
            
        
        &lt;/p&gt; 
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;A bit more searching led me to an &lt;a href=&#34;http://citeseerx.ist.psu.edu/viewdoc/download?doi=10.1.1.418.8179&amp;amp;rep=rep1&amp;amp;type=pdf&#34;&gt;actual article&lt;/a&gt; describing the experiment.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:2&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:2&#34;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Published in &lt;em&gt;Speculations in Science and Technology&lt;/em&gt;, it outlines a way to measure the relative motion of the Earth through the aether. Silvertooth argues that if the speed of light changes, the wavelength of light must also change, analogous to the &lt;a href=&#34;https://briankoberlein.com/2013/09/05/doppler-effect/&#34;&gt;Doppler effect&lt;/a&gt;. He then describes how he compared wavelengths in the direction of Earth&amp;rsquo;s motion with wavelengths perpendicular to Earth&amp;rsquo;s motion. Since relativity assumes the speed of light is a constant, there shouldn&amp;rsquo;t be any difference. But Silvertooth seems to find a difference, and measures the Earth&amp;rsquo;s speed to be 378 km/s in the direction of the constellation Leo. Interestingly, &lt;a href=&#34;https://briankoberlein.com/2013/10/13/relative-motion/&#34;&gt;observations of the cosmic microwave background&lt;/a&gt; shows that Earth is moving through the universe in that direction at 371 km/s. How very fascinating! This experiment shouldn&amp;rsquo;t work, and yet it seems to overturn special relativity. Could Einstein have been wrong after all?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Silvertooth experiment is part of a range of experiments related to the &lt;a href=&#34;https://briankoberlein.com/2015/02/14/burden-proof/&#34;&gt;one-way speed of light&lt;/a&gt;. The idea is that early experiments on relativity, such as the famous &lt;a href=&#34;https://briankoberlein.com/2013/10/14/aether-or/&#34;&gt;Michelson-Morley experiment&lt;/a&gt;, only measured the total travel time of light not the travel time in a single direction. What if the speed of light is slower in one direction, but faster in the opposite direction? What if the aether flowed past us like a river. The speed of light would be faster when moving downstream and slower coming back upstream, but the total travel time would be the same as if there were no aether at all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The story of how early relativity experiments proved the aether doesn&amp;rsquo;t exist isn&amp;rsquo;t really true. What they showed was that the aether isn&amp;rsquo;t needed to explain the results. By the 1970s it was demonstrated&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:3&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:3&#34;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; that if an aether exists it must be completely undetectable by relativity experiments. The results would still agree with Einstein. So over the decades interest in the aether mostly waned. Why assume there is an aether when relativity does just fine without it?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But then how to explain Silvertooth&amp;rsquo;s results? It could be that he just got bad results, but the experiment was done several times and seemed to be consistent. And Silvertooth was no slacker. He was a physicist who joined Paramount Studios as an engineer during the great depression, won an Oscar for Technical Merit in 1942, and then went on to work for an Air Force think tank. But Silvertooth was also rather terse about the results, and since hundreds of experiments agree with relativity his results were probably wrong. The experiment faded into history, remembered mainly by the kind of people who think Aristotle was right about astrophysics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is usually where the story ends. Obscure experiments like this don&amp;rsquo;t often get repeated, and when they do they&amp;rsquo;re usually done by people who aren&amp;rsquo;t trained experimentalists. But in 2012 Doug Marett actually repeated the experiment&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:4&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:4&#34;&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;, and &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.conspiracyoflight.com/Silvertooth/Silvertooth.html&#34;&gt;what he found&lt;/a&gt; is fascinating.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over the course of 18 months Marett recreated the Silvertooth experiment, and confirmed the result. There was an apparent shift in wavelength that varied with the orientation of Earth, and it did seem to show an apparent motion of Earth in agreement with Silvertooth&amp;rsquo;s intial findings. But looking at the data more carefully, Marett also found that there was a lot of fluctuation in the data.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure class=&#34;right&#34;&gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;/image/silvertoothtemp.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;The correlation of apparent shift with room temperature. Credit: Doug Marett&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;
        The correlation of apparent shift with room temperature. Credit: Doug Marett
        
            
        
        &lt;/p&gt; 
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Silvertooth&amp;rsquo;s original claim was that the wavelengths varied over the course of a sidereal day. A &lt;a href=&#34;https://briankoberlein.com/2013/11/27/a-suns-day/&#34;&gt;sidereal day&lt;/a&gt; is measured relative to the motion of the stars. Our normal solar day is based upon the motion of the Sun. Because of the Earth&amp;rsquo;s motion around the Sun, a solar day is about 4 minutes longer than a sidereal day. If Silvertooth was right, the wavelength variations should follow sidereal time, not solar time. Marett found there was so much noise in the data, the variation in wavelengths could be made to agree with either sidereal or solar time. Digging into things more closely, he saw a correlation between the observed wavelength shift and small fluctuations in the temperature of the room. The change in temperature was shifting the alignment of the experiment laser, causing the apparent shift Silvertooth saw. Marett also found that the calculated motion of the Earth only worked because Silvertooth assumed the data measured an actual wavelength shift. Silvertooth&amp;rsquo;s results were real, but his conclusions were wrong.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This doesn&amp;rsquo;t mean the aether doesn&amp;rsquo;t exist, but for now it is clear we don&amp;rsquo;t need an aether to explain Silvertooth&amp;rsquo;s experiment. In a broader sense, this story is an excellent example of the striking difference between science and pseudoscience. In pseduoscience folks are content to cite an article without any consideration of the actual results. If it seems to agree with your expectations, then that&amp;rsquo;s good enough. As a scientist, Marett took the time to look at an old experiment with a questioning eye. In doing so he solved a 30-year old mystery of the experiment that seemed to prove Einstein wrong.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;footnotes&#34;&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:1&#34;&gt;Silvertooth, E. W. &amp;ldquo;Special relativity.&amp;rdquo; Nature 322.6080 (1986): 590-590.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:1&#34;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:2&#34;&gt;Silvertooth, Ernest Wilbur. &amp;ldquo;Experimental detection of the ether.&amp;rdquo; Speculations in Science and Technology 10.1 (1986): 3.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:2&#34;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:3&#34;&gt;Winnie, John A. &amp;ldquo;Special relativity without one-way velocity assumptions: Part II.&amp;rdquo; Philosophy of Science 37.2 (1970): 223-238.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:3&#34;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:4&#34;&gt;Marett, Doug. &amp;ldquo;A Replication of the Silvertooth Experiment.&amp;rdquo;
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:4&#34;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Invisible Star</title>
      <link>/the-invisible-star/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Apr 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/the-invisible-star/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;There&amp;rsquo;s a limit to how far into the cosmos we can see. One of the biggest limiting factors is simply the brightness of an object. The more distant an object, the dimmer the object will appear. Even if there is no gas or dust in the way, the brightness decreases proportional to the square of its distance. For example, if two stars are equally bright, and one is twice as far away as the other, we will observe four times the light from the closer star than we see from the distant star. Because of this, main sequence stars such as our Sun can only be observed out to a few hundred million light years. Galaxies can be seen from billions of light years away, as can brilliant supernovae, but not a simple star.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But sometimes fortune favors the fortunate. There is a way that gravity can make an object appear brighter than it actually is. Just as a telescope can magnify light of a distant object, so can a &lt;a href=&#34;https://briankoberlein.com/2013/09/09/gravitational-lensing/&#34;&gt;gravitational lens&lt;/a&gt;. Gravitational lensing occurs when light from a distant is deflected by the presence of mass along our line of sight. It was &lt;a href=&#34;https://briankoberlein.com/2014/05/19/einstein-eddington/&#34;&gt;first observed by Arthur Eddington&lt;/a&gt; in 1919, and was the first validation of general relativity. As light is deflected around a galaxy or other mass, we see it coming from multiple directions. This means more light reaches us than normally would without lensing. So the star looks brighter than we&amp;rsquo;d expect.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure class=&#34;right&#34;&gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;/image/gravitationallens.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;A schematic example of gravitational lensing.&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;
        A schematic example of gravitational lensing.
        
            
        
        &lt;/p&gt; 
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This particular star, informally known as Icarus, is behind a large cluster of galaxies &lt;a href=&#34;https://blog.briankoberlein.com/whats-name/&#34;&gt;called&lt;/a&gt; MACS J1149+2223, and while the mass of the cluster brightened the star a bit, it wasn&amp;rsquo;t enough to be easily seen by the Hubble Space Telescope. But then a star from the cluster happened to pass in front of the distant star. This created an effect known as an Einstein ring, where light from Icarus grazes the closer star and is focused in our direction. The result is a significant brightening of the star. The combination of gravitational lensing from the galaxy cluster and the Einstein ring made Icarus appear 2000 times brighter than it actually is, making it bright enough for Hubble to capture. It&amp;rsquo;s light traveled for 9 billion years to reach us, making it the most distant main sequence star we&amp;rsquo;ve ever observed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sadly, Icarus itself is long dead. Analysis of the light shows that Icarus was a blue supergiant, similar to the bright star Rigel in the constellation of Orion. These stars can be 10,000 times brighter than our Sun, but their brilliance comes at a cost. They typically only shine for a few million years before dying as a brilliant supernova. The flicker of Icarus captured by Hubble is a luminous echo of a star that died when the universe was only 4 billion years old. Long before our own Sun began to form.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>What&#39;s in a Name?</title>
      <link>/whats-name/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 31 Mar 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/whats-name/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Yesterday I wrote about a &lt;a href=&#34;https://blog.briankoberlein.com/out-dark&#34;&gt;galaxy containing almost no dark matter&lt;/a&gt;. I didn&amp;rsquo;t mention its name, but it happens to be NGC1052-DF2. Of all the possible names you could give a galaxy, why that one? It all has to do with the history of how the galaxy was discovered.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some galaxies have wonderful names: Andromeda, Triangulum, and the Milky Way. Others are commonly known by a descriptive name, such as the Sombrero Galaxy with its distinctive rim of dust, or the Tadpole Galaxy with it&amp;rsquo;s long trail of stars. Others are named after its discover, such as Mayall&amp;rsquo;s Object, or Hoag&amp;rsquo;s Object. But there are billions of known galaxies in the heavens, so most, such as NGC1052-DF2, are known by a catalog name.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The history of galaxy catalogs has its origin with &lt;a href=&#34;https://briankoberlein.com/2014/11/18/act-frustration/&#34;&gt;Charles Messier&lt;/a&gt;. In the 1700s, Messier was looking for comets, which look like faint nebulous blurs before they become brighter and grow long tails. Other objects known as nebulae also look like faint blurs. To keep from confusing the two, Messier created a list of nebulae. That way when he found a faint blur he could compare it with his nebula catalogue to see if it really was a comet. This became known as the Messier Catalog, and contains 110 objects. Each object is denoted by an M for Messier, and then it&amp;rsquo;s catalog number. So the Andromeda Galaxy is known as M31. Not all of Messier&amp;rsquo;s objects are galaxies. Telescopes at the time weren&amp;rsquo;t powerful enough to distinguish between galaxies and other objects such as globular clusters and planetary nebulae. But 40 of the Messier objects are galaxies, making them the first galaxy catalog.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 1864, John Herschel published the &lt;em&gt;General Catalogue of Nebulae and Clusters of Stars&lt;/em&gt;, containing 5,079 objects. It expanded on the earlier work of his father William Herschel. This was expanded to 7,840 objects in 1888 by John Dreyer, and became known as the New General Catalogue, or NGC. The New General Catalogue was revised in 1973 and 1988, and is the most comprehensive list of nearby (in cosmic terms) galaxies. This is why galaxies often have the name NGC followed by a number.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But our particular galaxy has a hypened addition, and that&amp;rsquo;s because it isn&amp;rsquo;t in the main catalogue. It is a companion galaxy to NGC1052. Lots of the NGC galaxies have smaller companions, just as the Large and Small Magellanic clouds are companion galaxies to our own Milky Way. Since the galaxy was discovered by a telescope known as the Dragonfly Telephoto Array, and it was the second companion galaxy to be found, our galaxy has the name NGC1052-DF2.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Catalogs are a powerful tool of astronomers. They help us keep track of objects in the sky, and make sure different objects don&amp;rsquo;t get confused with each other. The only real downside is that they lead to some rather cumbersome names.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Out of the Dark</title>
      <link>/out-dark/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 30 Mar 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/out-dark/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Dark matter is the &lt;a href=&#34;https://briankoberlein.com/2014/08/15/five-facts/&#34;&gt;mystery&lt;/a&gt; that holds the universe together. Although it can&amp;rsquo;t be seen directly, we know it is there through its gravitational effect on light and the motion of matter. Dark matter makes up most of a galaxy&amp;rsquo;s mass, and there are some galaxies that are &lt;a href=&#34;https://briankoberlein.com/2016/09/02/dark-galaxy/&#34;&gt;almost entirely dark matter&lt;/a&gt;. This makes sense, because the atoms and molecules of stars and dust comprise only 12% of the mass in the universe. In the standard cosmological model, clumps of dark matter triggered the formation of galaxies and galactic clusters in the early universe, where there are galaxies there is dark matter. But recently astronomers have found a galaxy with almost no dark matter, and it&amp;rsquo;s raising questions about how it could have formed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The galaxy in question is an &lt;a href=&#34;https://briankoberlein.com/2017/09/03/puzzle-fluffy-galaxies/&#34;&gt;ultradiffuse galaxy&lt;/a&gt;. These are galaxies that can be as big as our Milky Way, but contain only a few billion stars, rather than the 400 billion of our home galaxy. Because they are diffuse and faint we have only recently been able to study them. Most of these ultradiffuse galaxies contain dark matter, but this new galaxy is different.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The amount of dark matter in a galaxy can be estimated by studying the &lt;a href=&#34;https://briankoberlein.com/2015/06/09/amassing-evidence/&#34;&gt;motion of globular clusters&lt;/a&gt; in a galaxy. These are tight clusters of stars that are scattered around a galaxy like a halo. The more mass a galaxy has, the faster these clusters move as they orbit the galaxy. By comparing the speed of globular clusters with the brightness of stars in a galaxy, we can compare the visible mass of a galaxy to its total mass. When the team did this for the new galaxy, they found the motion of its globular clusters agreed with the visible mass of stars and dust. No dark matter is needed to make up the difference.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The existence of a galaxy free from dark matter further confirms that dark matter is both real and different from regular matter. If dark matter were an illusion due to &lt;a href=&#34;https://briankoberlein.com/2014/08/16/old-model-doesnt-work/&#34;&gt;modified gravity&lt;/a&gt; then such a galaxy couldn&amp;rsquo;t exist. Dark matter is out there, just not in this particular galaxy. But if that&amp;rsquo;s true, then how could this galaxy have formed. One idea is that the galaxy could have been involved in a collision with another galaxy, which stripped away its dark matter. But a survey of the surrounding area shows no evidence of a collision.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The only way to solve this mystery is to look for other dark-matter free galaxies. Until then we&amp;rsquo;re not yet out of the dark.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Wheel of Time</title>
      <link>/wheel-time/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 15 Mar 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/wheel-time/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The universe moves like clockwork. Their motions can be described by elegant gravitational equations, which trace the motions of everything from planets to galaxies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The gravitational attraction between any two bodies is stronger when they are closer together, a property known as the &lt;a href=&#34;https://briankoberlein.com/2014/03/27/mutual-attraction-2/&#34;&gt;inverse square law&lt;/a&gt;. As a result, objects orbit each other more quickly when they are close together. The planet &lt;a href=&#34;https://briankoberlein.com/2014/03/21/icy-hot/&#34;&gt;Mercury&lt;/a&gt; orbits the Sun once every 88 days, while distant &lt;a href=&#34;https://briankoberlein.com/2014/04/04/neptune-night/&#34;&gt;Neptune&lt;/a&gt; takes 165 years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Galaxies don&amp;rsquo;t follow this relation. Most of the visible matter in a galaxy is concentrated at its center, just like our solar system. So you would expect that stars close to the center of a galaxy would move much more quickly than those on the outer edge. But it turns out that both central and edge stars move at about the same speed. This is due to the fact that galaxies are largely comprised of &lt;a href=&#34;https://briankoberlein.com/2014/08/15/five-facts/&#34;&gt;dark matter&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure class=&#34;right&#34;&gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;/image/rotationrelation.png&#34; alt=&#34;The relation between rotation speed and galaxy size.&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;
        The relation between rotation speed and galaxy size.
        
            
        
        &lt;/p&gt; 
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Even with dark matter, galaxies vary widely in mass. So one would still expect stars in dense and massive galaxies to orbit more quickly than stars in more diffuse galaxies. But it turns out that isn&amp;rsquo;t the case.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; New observations of galaxies found that regardless of a galaxy&amp;rsquo;s size, the stars on the outer edge of the galaxy take about a billion years to orbit the galaxy once. The relation holds for small dwarf galaxies just as well as it holds for massive spiral galaxies. We aren&amp;rsquo;t entirely sure why. Some simple models of galactic evolution allow for such a relation, but we will need more data to pin down the exact mechanism.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This isn&amp;rsquo;t the first time we&amp;rsquo;ve found a relation among galaxies without fully understanding the underlying cause. The most famous one is the &lt;a href=&#34;https://briankoberlein.com/2013/11/17/tully-fisher-king/&#34;&gt;Tully-Fisher relation&lt;/a&gt;, which connects rotation speed to the overall brightness of a galaxy. But even without a known mechanism, this relation could be quite useful. By measuring the speed of stars on the edge of a galaxy, we can easily pin down its overall size. This can be difficult to do with distant galaxies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;footnotes&#34;&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:1&#34;&gt;Meurer, Gerhardt R., et al. &amp;ldquo;Cosmic clocks: a tight radius–velocity relationship for H i-selected galaxies.&amp;rdquo; Monthly Notices of the Royal Astronomical Society 476.2 (2018): 1624-1636. DOI: &lt;a href=&#34;https://arxiv.org/abs/1803.04716&#34;&gt;10.1093/mnras/sty275&lt;/a&gt;
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:1&#34;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Beginnings and Endings</title>
      <link>/beginning-ending/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 14 Mar 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/beginning-ending/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Each of us has a beginning and an ending. We awake to explore the universe for a brief time, then return to our cosmic slumber. Stephen Hawking was no different. He was born in January of 1942, and he died on 14 March 2018. He was fascinated with beginnings and endings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For his doctoral dissertation, Hawking focused on the nature of the &lt;a href=&#34;https://briankoberlein.com/2014/03/24/primeval-atom/&#34;&gt;big bang&lt;/a&gt;, specifically whether it began as a singularity. A singularity is where the very nature of space and time break down. The curvature of space at a singularity becomes infinite, and matter at a singularity has infinite density. They first appeared in the &lt;a href=&#34;https://briankoberlein.com/2015/01/22/pointed-debate/&#34;&gt;context of black holes&lt;/a&gt; (still hypothetical at the time) where it was thought that the matter of a large dead star would collapse forever under its own weight. Hawking showed that general relativity required the big bang to be a singularity, hence the idea that the universe began as a single point of infinite energy density. Years later Hawking and others demonstrated that a big bang singularity wasn&amp;rsquo;t necessary. Because of quantum mechanics, a singularity might not even be possible. Whether the universe began as a singularity or merely as a hot dense state is still an issue of much debate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The work Hawking is most known for concerned black holes. In general relativity, black holes have an &lt;a href=&#34;https://briankoberlein.com/2014/02/03/edge/&#34;&gt;event horizon&lt;/a&gt;. That is, a boundary surrounding a black hole that is a cosmic point of no return. Cross the event horizon, and you are forever trapped. But this caused several problems in theoretical physics. For example, if an event horizon were truly a point of no return, and not even light can escape, then black holes would be absolutely cold. According to thermodynamics, every object gives off some light as thermal heat. General relativity said that black holes have a temperature of absolute zero, which thermodynamics says is impossible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hawking found that this contradiction could be solved through quantum mechanics. General relativity is a classical theory, meaning that objects have an absolute position in space and time. But in quantum theory the location of objects is fuzzy. The &lt;a href=&#34;https://briankoberlein.com/2014/05/02/making-waves/&#34;&gt;wavelike nature&lt;/a&gt; of quantum objects means they can&amp;rsquo;t be pinned down to a specific location. This means that quantum objects can&amp;rsquo;t be trapped forever within a black hole. There is always a small chance that &lt;a href=&#34;https://briankoberlein.com/2014/08/28/great-escape/&#34;&gt;they could escape&lt;/a&gt;, taking a bit of the black hole&amp;rsquo;s mass with it. This escaped radiation came to be known as Hawking radiation. Through Hawking radiation black holes not only had a temperature, but their temperature increased as they radiated away. Thus black holes are not immortal. Like everything else in the universe, they exist for a finite time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course the beginning and ending of things is rooted in the nature of time. While it seems obvious that time flows from past to present to future, in physics things aren&amp;rsquo;t so clear. The mathematical equations we use are time symmetric, meaning they work just as well going from past to future as they do going from future to past. It seems that there is nothing inherent to the laws of physics that requires a direction to time. This is known as the &lt;a href=&#34;https://briankoberlein.com/2015/06/12/times-arrow/&#34;&gt;arrow of time problem&lt;/a&gt;. Why do we experience a direction in time?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The answer seems to lie within thermodynamics. One of the fundamental rules of thermodynamics is that heat flows from warmer objects to colder objects. This is related to the &lt;a href=&#34;https://briankoberlein.com/2014/03/31/dying-light/&#34;&gt;amount of entropy&lt;/a&gt; a system has. Entropy increases over time, and this seems to give a direction to time. In studying this problem Hawking found entropy could account for the arrow of time, but it could also have strange effects. If an expanding universe experiences an arrow of time that moves from past to future, a contracting universe could have an arrow of time that points from future to past.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Throughout his life, Stephen Hawking explored some of the most challenging and subtle questions in physics and cosmology. He focused on ideas and their implications, not experiments. As a result, none of his ideas have been proven experimentally. Some of his ideas such as Hawking radiation are widely thought to be correct, but that is far from being proven. The legacy Hawking leaves us is in many ways a challenge. Prove that his ideas are correct, or find better answers to the questions he raised.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And in that way the story of Stephen Hawking is just beginning.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Waking the Dead</title>
      <link>/waking-dead/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 07 Mar 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/waking-dead/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Every star dies. Our Sun will shine for about 5 billion more years, but the time will come when it swells to a red giant for a time, then collapse to become a white dwarf. Larger stars live shorter lives, and can eventually collapse to become neutron stars.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;White dwarfs and neutron stars can truly be considered dead stars. Unlike regular stars, they don&amp;rsquo;t generate heat internally through nuclear fusion. They don&amp;rsquo;t have active periods with solar flares. They simply cool slowly over billions of years.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure class=&#34;right&#34;&gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;/image/NSandMH.gif&#34; alt=&#34;A neutron star compared in size to Manhattan island.&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;
        A neutron star compared in size to Manhattan island.
        
            
        
        &lt;/p&gt; 
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;That is, unless they have a companion star. When two stars orbit each other closely, material from one star can sometimes transfer to the other. This most often occurs when a red giant and white dwarf orbit closely. Material from the outer layers of the red giant can captured by the white dwarf. If the white dwarf captures enough material, it can cause the white dwarf to collapse, triggering a supernova. In principle a similar effect should be possible with a neutron star, where material captured from a red dwarf companion causes the neutron star to be active again. Now this effect has been observed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As described in a paper&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; from Astronomy &amp;amp; Astrophysics, the team observed x-rays emitting from a previously quiet neutron star. The x-rays are generated when the neutron star captures matter from its companion. While this type of interaction isn&amp;rsquo;t surprising, it demonstrates how dynamic these binary systems can be, and it may help us better understand how these &amp;ldquo;odd-couple&amp;rdquo; binaries evolve over time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;footnotes&#34;&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:1&#34;&gt;Bozzo, E., et al. &amp;ldquo;IGR J17329-2731: The birth of a symbiotic X-ray binary.&amp;rdquo; arXiv preprint arXiv:1803.01593 (2018). &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1051/0004-6361/201832588&#34;&gt;DOI: 10.1051&amp;#47;0004-6361&amp;#47;201832588&lt;/a&gt;.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:1&#34;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Changes in the Wind</title>
      <link>/changes-wind/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 26 Feb 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/changes-wind/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;If you&amp;rsquo;re reading this, welcome to the new website.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I began One Universe at a Time five years ago, it was really as a way to archive things I&amp;rsquo;d been &lt;a href=&#34;https://plus.google.com/+BrianKoberlein&#34;&gt;writing on Google+&lt;/a&gt;. To make things easy, I set it up on a Wordpress server. It&amp;rsquo;s quick, simple, and there are lots of hosting options. Wordpress is great if you have a relatively small site, but thousands of posts and ever increasing bandwidth starts taking a toll. Over the past several months the backend of the website has gotten ever slower, with no end in site. When my hosting provider announced yet another price increase, the time was right to move.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that meant the opportunity to do things in a different way. Hopefully a better one. Rather than simply moving to yet another Wordpress site, I&amp;rsquo;ve decided to roll my own as it were. This will not only eliminate the computational overhead of Wordpress, it will force me to focus more on what I write and how I write it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wordpress makes it so easy to do a post that you don&amp;rsquo;t have to think much about it. As a result, my writing has gotten lazier. I&amp;rsquo;d find myself writing something quickly rather than giving an idea room to grow. The new site is much more solid, but it requires a higher level of intentionality. That means the writing will be more intentional as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course you can&amp;rsquo;t completely change a website from the ground up without some growing pains. Comments have been off for a while to make the transition easier. There could also be some hiccups of missing articles or images. If you find any issues, please let me know.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So welcome to the new site. I look forward to telling you the next five years of stories.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Greatest Show On Earth</title>
      <link>/greatest-show-earth/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 02 Feb 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/greatest-show-earth/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Yesterday an eccentric billionaire launched his electric car into space, and you could watch it live on the internet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Elon Musk is nothing if not bold. He is also a master showman, transforming a risky first launch of the Falcon Heavy into a $90 million commercial for his car company. With his big dreams and slick marketing, Musk seems like a character out of science fiction or comic books. But behind the showman is a team of highly skilled workers. They not only do some amazing engineering, they also do some amazing science.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We often think of science and engineering as two separate things. Science asks deep questions and expands the horizon of human understanding, while engineering applies scientific understanding to technological problems. But often the line is blurred. Often scientific research requires complex and cutting edge engineering.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, at Green Bank Observatory one research project known as Mustang II studies the very cold gas and dust in our galaxy. To do this, the Mustang II detector has to be kept extremely cold. Only ⅕ of a degree above absolute zero. In order to gather data, the research team had to design and build a detector that can remain that cold while mounted on the boom of the 100-meter Green Bank Telescope. It&amp;rsquo;s a difficult piece of engineering, which is part of the reason Mustang II can be finicky and difficult to maintain. Science depends upon engineering.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure class=&#34;right&#34;&gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;/image/spacexworkers.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;More than 7,000 people work at SpaceX.&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;
        More than 7,000 people work at SpaceX.
        
            
        
        &lt;/p&gt; 
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;While many companies just rely on good design and engineering. That isn&amp;rsquo;t the case for Musk&amp;rsquo;s companies such as Tesla or SpaceX. In order for electric cars to succeed, we will need to develop more efficient batteries, and that requires new research in material science. New discoveries in artificial intelligence are needed to allow cars to drive themselves. Likewise, SpaceX has an aggressive plan to launch ever more powerful rockets, and that will require more efficient rocket engines with cheaper fuels and lighter materials. These companies aren&amp;rsquo;t just designing products, they are undertaking scientific research to achieve their goals. Elon Musk understands this, and it allows his companies to pursue goals that are both high risk and high reward.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Musk has made it clear that his long term goal is to put humans on Mars, and that&amp;rsquo;s going to take more than showmanship. It&amp;rsquo;s going to take Big Science.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Illusion of Truth</title>
      <link>/the-illusion-of-truth/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Jul 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/the-illusion-of-truth/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Physical theories are often presented as a description of what&amp;rsquo;s really going on. Forces act on a baseball, causing it to fall. Atoms collide and fuse in the heart of a star, releasing heat and energy. Science is true, as is often said, and our scientific theories encapsulate this truth. But this isn&amp;rsquo;t entirely true.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure class=&#34;right&#34;&gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;/image/HydrogenDensityPlots.png&#34; alt=&#34;The probability distributions for hydrogen in different energy states.&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;
        The probability distributions for hydrogen in different energy states.
        
            
        
        &lt;/p&gt; 
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;For example, quantum mechanics is a &lt;a href=&#34;https://briankoberlein.com/2013/11/16/taking-the-quantum-leap/&#34;&gt;strange&lt;/a&gt;, sometimes confusing theory. Objects can be &lt;a href=&#34;https://briankoberlein.com/2014/03/07/duality/&#34;&gt;particles and waves&lt;/a&gt;. They do strange things like &lt;a href=&#34;https://briankoberlein.com/2013/10/17/the-suns-magic/&#34;&gt;tunnel through barriers&lt;/a&gt;, and can even &lt;a href=&#34;https://briankoberlein.com/2014/08/28/great-escape/&#34;&gt;appear and disappear&lt;/a&gt;.  Given all this strangeness, what&amp;rsquo;s really going on? What&amp;rsquo;s the true nature of quantum reality? It depends on which approach you want to take. In one view quantum objects are described by a wave-like probability function. When you interact with or &amp;ldquo;observe&amp;rdquo; the object this &amp;ldquo;wavefunction&amp;rdquo; collapses into a definite state. That&amp;rsquo;s view commonly presented, but a quantum system can also be described by its transitions between energy states. Since this uses a mathematical method involving matrices, it&amp;rsquo;s known as matrix mechanics. Both wavefunctions and matrix mechanics give the same results, but their view of what really goes on is very different. Then there&amp;rsquo;s the &lt;a href=&#34;https://briankoberlein.com/2015/02/27/dance-of-the-hag/&#34;&gt;path integral method&lt;/a&gt;. Rather than a wavefunction or matrix transitions, path integrals imagine quantum objects can take almost any path between two states. By summing all the possible paths you can derive the odds that it will occur.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure class=&#34;right&#34;&gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;/image/heliumlev.gif&#34; alt=&#34;The matrix transition version of quantum theory doesn&amp;#39;t care about the wavefunction.&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;
        The matrix transition version of quantum theory doesn&amp;#39;t care about the wavefunction.
        
            
        
        &lt;/p&gt; 
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;So which one is true? Are quantum objects distributed waves of probability? Are they simply transitions between energy states? Do they take an infinite number of paths between states? Each of these models make the same predictions, so one version is no more &amp;ldquo;true&amp;rdquo; than the others. What happens in practice is that we&amp;rsquo;ll use whatever method is useful at the time. They are equivalent models, so the best model for the job is the one we&amp;rsquo;ll use. The only reason the wavefunction view is so common is that it&amp;rsquo;s the version usually taught to introductory students.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You might think this uncertainty of truth is due to the behavior of quantum physics itself. It&amp;rsquo;s so strange and counterintuitive that we can&amp;rsquo;t wrap our puny brains around what&amp;rsquo;s really going on. But the same thing occurs in lots of other fields. Even something as straight forward as basic Newtonian physics.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure class=&#34;right&#34;&gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;/image/pathintegrals.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;In the path integral view many potential paths are summed.&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;
        In the path integral view many potential paths are summed.
        
            
        
        &lt;/p&gt; 
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Toss a baseball in the air and Earth&amp;rsquo;s gravitational force pulls it down. The force of gravity is a simple truth, right? While we often describe classical motion in terms of forces and acceleration, we can also describe it in terms of energy and momentum. In the Lagrangian and Hamiltonian approach, the path of a baseball is the optimized path among possibilities. In this view a baseball&amp;rsquo;s path is the extrema of an energy equation, and force can be derived as a necessary consequence of this. In the relativistic view the baseball follows a geodesic, which is the minimal path through space and time. So is a baseball&amp;rsquo;s motion due to a gravitational force, an energy extrema, or a spacetime geodesic? As with quantum theory, different approaches yield the same result. They are mathematically equivalent, so we can use whatever method is most useful at the time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At its core, science is less about truth and more about models. The metaphysics underlying a model is useful only as far as it allows us to make better predictions, generate new ideas, or bring models together as a cohesive whole. This is why we have no problem using classical gravity to calculate the path of a spacecraft through the solar system, while using special relativity to account for the Doppler shift of the spacecraft&amp;rsquo;s radio signals. It&amp;rsquo;s why we can use quantum physics to study atoms in the morning, and general relativity to study black holes in the afternoon. In regimes where models conflict with each other it isn&amp;rsquo;t a failure of truth, but instead shows an opportunity to develop a better model.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It could be that with each better model we move closer to the truth about reality. The truth is out there, and science strives to move towards that truth. It&amp;rsquo;s a common view, and certainly the search for truth has driven many scientists to develop better and better models. But the real power of science is the recognition that what we have are models. Our models can be powerful, but they are always a bit tentative. There&amp;rsquo;s always a chance that they might just be an illusion of truth.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Turing the Universe</title>
      <link>/turing-universe/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 05 Jul 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/turing-universe/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;My research area is computational astrophysics. This means I use computers to analyze astronomical data or model astrophysical systems. Most of my work is done through an application known as Mathematica, which is a powerful computational program. Like any application, Mathematica has advantages and disadvantages, but it has one property that is absolutely essential: it is Turing complete.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A program that is Turing complete is capable (at least in principle) of computing anything that can be computed. So the only real limitation to an astrophysical model is computing power and memory. As a result, I can run a model in Mathematica on my laptop. If it takes too long, or needs too much memory, I can run the same model on a cluster of computers. With enough grant money I could run it on a large supercomputing cluster. My only limitation is that of the current hardware.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Turing completeness is central to computational astrophysics, though it is not a particularly rare property for applications. For example, Excel and Minecraft are Turing complete. One consequence of this is that any Turing complete application can model any other Turing complete application, so in principle you could program Excel to run Minecraft, and then program Minecraft to run Mathematica. It would be horribly impractical to do that, but it’s possible in principle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The idea of computational completeness was developed by Alan Turing. He was a mathematician and computer scientist who lived in the mid-1900s, and was central to the cracking of the German enigma code in WWII. It was his work on computability that lead to his understanding of enigma.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Knowing an application is Turing complete, you can then choose your application based on other needs, such as ease of coding, or scalability. These are two of the reasons I use Mathematica. It is geared toward scientific computing, and the same program can be run on a laptop or computer cluster without recoding.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Completeness gives us the confidence that computational models can provide an accurate description of astrophysical processes. We are not simply limited to models that can be done by hand. We can use computers to extend our understanding of the universe.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Turn, Turn, Turn</title>
      <link>/turn-turn-turn/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 02 Sep 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/turn-turn-turn/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The gravitational attraction an object has on you depends on how much mass it has, and how far away you are away from it. If the mass is spherical, then the closest you can get to its center (without digging) is its surface. This means that the gravitational strength of a spherical star/planet depends on its mass and its density. The higher an object&amp;rsquo;s density, the smaller its radius, and the stronger gravity is on its surface.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure class=&#34;right&#34;&gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;/image/pulsardiagram.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Diagram of a pulsar. Credit: NRAO&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;
        Diagram of a pulsar. Credit: NRAO
        
            
        
        &lt;/p&gt; 
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Now suppose we spin our spherical world. If we are standing on its surface, we would have a tendency to fly off the world due to its rotation. The gravity is stronger than the centrifugal force, so we stay put. But if we could spin the world faster and faster, we would reach a point where the centrifugal force is equal to the force of gravity. Spin the world any faster, and we would fly off. This means that for a given density for a planet/star, there is a maximum rate of rotation. Any faster and it would fly apart. Put another way, if we measure the rotation of a planet or star, we know its minimum density.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Very roughly, we can calculate that density in grams per cubic centimeter by taking 140 million and dividing it by the square of an object&amp;rsquo;s period in seconds. So for the Earth, the period is 24 hours or 86,400 seconds. Plug that into our equation and we get a minimum density of about 0.02 g/cc. The Earth&amp;rsquo;s real density is about 5 g/cc, well above that minimum.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pulsars are kind of like cosmic light houses. As they rotate they sweep out a beam of radio waves from their magnetic poles. If those poles are pointing in our direction, we can &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.jb.man.ac.uk/pulsar/Education/Sounds/sounds.html&#34;&gt;hear each rotation as a pulse&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The fastest pulsars have a rotational period of about 1/1000th of a second. Plug that into our equation, and you get a minimum density of about 100 teragrams/cc. Thats 1 with 14 zeros after it. 100 trillion grams per sugar cube volume. That density is unimaginably high, but it also happens to be about the density of the nuclei of atoms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So pulsars are as dense as atomic nuclei, only several kilometers in diameter. We call them neutron stars.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Back of the Envelope</title>
      <link>/back-of-the-envelope/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Sep 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/back-of-the-envelope/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Astrophysics (like any science) is about getting the details right. As I’ve mentioned earlier, the difference between two theoretical models can be very small (look at the &lt;a href=&#34;https://blog.briankoberlein.com/span-of-a-heartbeat/&#34;&gt;precession of Mercury&lt;/a&gt; as a case in point). But there are times when you just do a rough calculation to see if you are on the right track.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure class=&#34;right&#34;&gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;/image/pressure.png&#34; alt=&#34;Pressure for an ideal star.&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;
        Pressure for an ideal star.
        
            
        
        &lt;/p&gt; 
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Suppose you wanted to determine the pressure and temperature inside the Sun. We could start with a very simple model: assume the Sun is an ideal gas, sitting there quietly under its own weight (known as hydrostatic equilibrium). You would think this is a horrible approximation. The Sun is nothing like an ideal gas, right? It certainly isn’t static. It has flares and convection and is fusing elements in its core. Still, let’s see what our simple model predicts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the figures here I’ve graphed the pressure and temperature of the Sun as a function of its radius. All I’ve assumed is that I have a mass of ideal gas equal to the mass of the Sun, held together by its own weight. In astrophysics lingo, this model is one example of what’s known as a polytropic star. The exact shape of the graphs depends on the type of ideal gas you choose, so for these graphs I chose a gas that’s 75% hydrogen and 25% helium, which is roughly the percentages of the Sun.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure class=&#34;left&#34;&gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;/image/temperature.png&#34; alt=&#34;Temperature for an ideal star.&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;
        Temperature for an ideal star.
        
            
        
        &lt;/p&gt; 
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The result is that we calculate a central pressure of about 2,500 gigapascal, and a central temperature of about 3.5 million Kelvin. Compared to accepted values, our pressure is too low by a factor of about 100, and our temperature too low by about a factor of 5. Not too bad for such a rough approximation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That said, even our rough calculation tells us something important. At the pressure and temperature we calculated it is possible for fusion to occur. Our back of the envelope calculation tells us that we should expect the core of our sun to undergo fusion. When this model was first calculated, it was a good first step to understanding what powers the Sun, and it pointed us in the right direction to develop better models.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sometimes even a simplistic model can be very useful.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Five Gripes About Children’s Television</title>
      <link>/five-gripes-about-childrens-television/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Sep 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/five-gripes-about-childrens-television/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Lab Coats&lt;/strong&gt;&amp;ndash; Perhaps the most common stereotype about scientists is that they always wear lab coats. This is reinforced in children&amp;rsquo;s shows, where the &amp;ldquo;scientist&amp;rdquo; host wears a lab coat. They wear it &lt;em&gt;everywhere&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;sup&gt;24&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;7&lt;/sub&gt;. Think &lt;em&gt;Bill Nye&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Beakman&amp;rsquo;s World&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Nina and the Neurons&lt;/em&gt;, etc. When you see a children&amp;rsquo;s television host wearing a lab coat, you know they&amp;rsquo;re a &amp;ldquo;scientist&amp;rdquo;. Of course this reinforces the idea that scientists are the &amp;ldquo;other&amp;rdquo;. You know scientists couldn&amp;rsquo;t possibly live in your neighborhood, since you never see anyone mowing their lawn or out for a morning jog in their lab coat.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Science = explosions&lt;/strong&gt;&amp;ndash; Let&amp;rsquo;s face it, explosions are cool. And nothing gets people&amp;rsquo;s attention faster than loud noises and fire. (Hey, it works for &lt;em&gt;Mythbusters&lt;/em&gt;). Of course in real scientific research, explosions are usually the last thing you want. Real science is about inquiry and observation, not simply blowing stuff up. A variation of this gripe is the common &amp;ldquo;science = magic&amp;rdquo; schtick where the lab-coated scientist shows you a trick. Magic? No, Science!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Girls rule, Boys drool&lt;/strong&gt;&amp;ndash; Fortunately there has been a shift away from the idea that only boys do science. There is still a disparity between girls and boys in STEM fields. Although overall more American women than men major in STEM at the college level, women are drawn to areas such as psychology rather than physics or engineering. To address this issue educators have introduced programs such as &amp;ldquo;Women in Engineering&amp;rdquo;, which has helped to raise the percentage of girls in those areas. Children&amp;rsquo;s science television has also shifted to address the interests of girls, and have even developed shows such as &lt;em&gt;SciGirls&lt;/em&gt; that focus on women in science. But sometimes in the effort to portray girls in a positive light they also portray boys in a negative light. In &lt;em&gt;SciGirls&lt;/em&gt; the effect is subtle. Izzie and the other girls use science to solve problems. The boy Jake, while nice, is a bit clueless about science, and usually needs help from the girls. In other shows, such as &lt;em&gt;Spaced Out: A Cosmic Scene&lt;/em&gt;, the effect is more blatant. Here the woman is a smart articulate scientist, while the boyish man is a silent mouth breather whose only role is to be ridiculed.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Actors as &amp;ldquo;scientists&amp;rdquo;&lt;/strong&gt;&amp;ndash; Just as the host always wears a lab coat, the host is always a &amp;ldquo;scientist&amp;rdquo;. Of course, they aren&amp;rsquo;t scientists, they&amp;rsquo;re professional actors (okay, Bill Nye is also an engineer). There isn&amp;rsquo;t anything wrong with actors playing the role of a scientist on a children&amp;rsquo;s television show, except when the host is always a &amp;ldquo;scientist&amp;rdquo;, and only the &amp;ldquo;scientist&amp;rdquo; leads the science. This reinforces the idea that only scientists can do science, when in fact anyone can. Imagine if we taught kids that only professional athletes do sports, while kids can only &amp;ldquo;play&amp;rdquo; doing sports (and only under the careful observation of a real athlete).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Answers from authority&lt;/strong&gt;&amp;ndash; When your host is a scientist, you always know that he or she will give you the right answer in the end. The expert will tell children what is right or wrong rather than encouraging children to develop their own answers based on inquiry and observation. Rather than demonstrating observation, inquiry and scientific thinking, many children&amp;rsquo;s shows simply have the scientist host dictate the answer from on high.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Losing Air</title>
      <link>/losing-air/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Sep 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/losing-air/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;We generally imagine that Earth&amp;rsquo;s atmosphere is a constant, but this isn&amp;rsquo;t so. It turns out air does escape our atmosphere, but it isn&amp;rsquo;t anything to worry about. For any planet, the larger its mass the easier it is to hold on to a gaseous atmosphere. This is part of the reason why Mars has such a thin atmosphere compared to Earth. It also depends on things like temperature (hotter gasses can escape more easily), density (lighter gasses escape faster than heavier gasses), and if the planet has a strong magnetic field (magnetic fields help hold gasses).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course that raises an interesting mystery. Venus is a little smaller than Earth, hotter than Earth, and doesn&amp;rsquo;t have a strong magnetic field like Earth, so it should have a &lt;em&gt;less&lt;/em&gt; dense atmosphere than Earth. In fact, the atmosphere of Venus is &lt;em&gt;much&lt;/em&gt; thicker than Earth&amp;rsquo;s. Why?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It turns out that Earth has something Venus doesn&amp;rsquo;t &amp;ndash; liquid water. Water is very good at absorbing gasses like carbon dioxide. Water also helps put gasses like CO2 into rocks. So, Earth&amp;rsquo;s atmosphere would be thicker than Venus except for the fact that so much gas is trapped in water and rocks. So the wetness of our planet not only helps to regulate our temperature, it ensures that we don&amp;rsquo;t get crushed by a thick atmosphere.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So how much time do we have? Given the rate at which we lose atmosphere, and all the spare atmosphere we have trapped in the oceans and rocks, we will have atmosphere for as long as the sun shines. That gives us about 5 billion years, so mark your calendars!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Perception of Depth</title>
      <link>/perception-of-depth/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 31 Aug 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/perception-of-depth/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;If you’ve ever watched a 3D movie, you’ve noticed how the image on the screen appears to have a certain depth to it. Certain objects just seem farther away. Other objects (usually pointy things) seem to leap out from the screen. You’ve also probably noticed that you have to wear a pair of glasses to watch the movie. If you take the glasses off during the movie, things look somewhat blurry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;3D movies work by projecting two movies at the same time. The two movies are almost identical, except that one was filmed (or computer generated) slightly to the left of center, and the other was filmed slightly to the right. This means that each movie has a slightly different point of view. The movies are projected on a special screen such that the light reflected from right projector is polarized one way, and the light from the left projector is polarized another. The glasses you wear are polarizing filters, and they ensure that only the left image reaches your left eye and only the right image reaches your right eye. With the glasses on, you see a different point of view in each eye. When you take the glasses off, you see both images at once, which is why they look blurry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This trick works because (most) humans have depth perception. Our brains are able to integrate these two points of view into a perception of near and far. The same effect exists in the real world, and helps us do things like catch baseballs (or duck for the less athletically inclined). But the effect is typically more dramatic in the theater.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Depth perception is possible because a closer object exhibits a parallax shift when compared to more distant object. You can see this effect by looking at a a distant object. Close one eye, and hold up your thumb to cover the distant object. Without moving your thumb, switch eyes. What you will see is that your thumb has shifted because of the different point of view. If you hold your thumb closer to your face you get a bigger shift. Farther away and you get a smaller shift. This relationship is true in general. The closer the object the bigger the parallax shift. So by observing the parallax of objects, your brain can gauge their distance.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure class=&#34;right&#34;&gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;/image/parallax.gif&#34; alt=&#34;An example of parallax. Credit: University of Virginia&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;
        An example of parallax. Credit: University of Virginia
        
            
        
        &lt;/p&gt; 
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;We can use the same effect to measure the distances of stars, using the width of Earth’s orbit. As the Earth moves around the Sun, you can measure the apparent position of a star against more distant stars. Over time you can observe the shift when the Earth is at one side of its orbit, and when its at the other side. That gives us two points of view separated by about 186 million miles (the actual distance varies depending on direction of the star in relation to Earth). This seems like a huge distance to us, but the parallax shift of stars is very small. Even the closest stars (not counting the Sun) are about 1 parsec away (a bit less than 4 light-years), which means they have a parallax shift of about 1 second of arc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’ve been able to use this cosmic depth perception to measure stellar distances up to about 1500 light years. Beyond that and the parallax shift is too small to measure accurately. Of course that raises the question of how we measure distances of farther objects. How can we say something is millions of light years away, or billions? For that we need several other methods, which together are known as the cosmic distance ladder.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But that’s a story for another time.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Span of a Heartbeat</title>
      <link>/span-of-a-heartbeat/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 31 Aug 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/span-of-a-heartbeat/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;One aspect of general relativity that always amazes me is the level of precision needed to distinguish it from Newtonian gravity. Take, for example, the advance of Mercury’s perihelion. When you count in the gravitational tugs from the sun and all the planets, Newton predicts Mercury’s perihelion will advance about 531.65 arcseconds per century. When we measure the orbit of Mercury, we find its perihelion &lt;em&gt;actually&lt;/em&gt; advances 574.10 arcseconds per century. This means Newton’s prediction is off by about 42.45 arcseconds per century. I say “about” because there is an uncertainty in our observations of about 0.65. General relativity predicts an “extra” perihelion advance of 42.98, which agrees exactly with experimental observation.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure class=&#34;right&#34;&gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;/image/precession.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Precession of a planet. Credit: Kenneth R. Lang&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;
        Precession of a planet. Credit: Kenneth R. Lang
        
            
        
        &lt;/p&gt; 
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The difference between Newton’s model and Einstein’s amounts to 28 millionths of a degree each orbital revolution. Put another way, Mercury makes one orbit every 87.969 days, but it reaches its perihelion about a half second later than Newton says it should. The difference between Newton and Einstein is less than a human heartbeat in time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The most amazing thing about all this? This deviation from Newton was first accurately measured by Urbain Le Verrier in 1859.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Small Beginnings</title>
      <link>/small-beginnings/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 30 Aug 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/small-beginnings/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;So I’ve finally made a personal website.  All the cool kids are doing it these days, and I didn’t want to be left behind.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve had personal websites before, but these have always been hosted by the various institutes where I’ve been employed, and over time these sites either relocated or faded away.  This is the first time I have a site with a domain and server I control, so I can ensure that pages won’t disappear, and the site won’t be relocated to another domain.  Here I stand, as it were.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some of you (perhaps most of you) may know that at the moment I spend most of my social media time on Google+, where &lt;a href=&#34;https://plus.google.com/+BrianKoberlein&#34;&gt;I write a great deal about astrophysics&lt;/a&gt;. That isn’t likely to change any time soon.  Google+ has a vibrant science community, and I will continue to write about astro-topics there primarily, or at least first.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But despite all the benefits of Google+, it is just one corner of the internet.  It is a rich garden, but a walled one.  So the initial goal of this site will be to move beyond the garden wall.  It will start small, and I’ll initially have posts about astronomy and astrophysics, since that’s what I’m most familiar with.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then we’ll just see where it goes.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>