<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Sun on Brian Koberlein</title>
    <link>/tags/sun/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Sun on Brian Koberlein</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <copyright>CC BY-NC 4.0</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 16 Apr 2018 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
        <atom:link href="/tags/sun/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>The Incredible Shrinking Sun</title>
      <link>/incredible-shrinking-sun/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 16 Apr 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/incredible-shrinking-sun/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Our Sun has provided Earth with light for billions of years. This light has allowed life to evolve and flourish on our small planet, but it comes at a cost.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Sun&amp;rsquo;s light is produced by &lt;a href=&#34;https://briankoberlein.com/2014/06/10/chain-reaction/&#34;&gt;fusion in the Sun&amp;rsquo;s core&lt;/a&gt;. Hydrogen atoms combine to produce helium and light. The light is produced because the mass of a helium atom is slightly smaller than the mass of the four hydrogen atoms that formed it. As Einstein first pointed out, &lt;a href=&#34;https://briankoberlein.com/2014/03/26/muse-fire/&#34;&gt;mass and energy can transform into each other&lt;/a&gt;, so the loss of mass means a gain of energy in the form of light. The light radiates from the Sun, warming our Earth, but that also means over time the Sun loses mass. The Sun consumes mass to produce light.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As the Sun loses mass its gravitational pull on the planets weakens slightly. The Sun can&amp;rsquo;t hold the planets as strongly as it used to, so the planets drift a bit further away from the Sun. At least that&amp;rsquo;s the theory. The shift of the planets is so small that it&amp;rsquo;s difficult to measure. There have been some studies that &lt;a href=&#34;https://briankoberlein.com/2016/01/01/relative-units/&#34;&gt;seemed to see the effect with Earth&lt;/a&gt;, but the result isn&amp;rsquo;t particularly strong. The usual method of determining planetary distance is to &lt;a href=&#34;https://briankoberlein.com/2015/11/13/casting-radio-shadows-to-map-the-moon-and-venus/&#34;&gt;bounce radio signals off them&lt;/a&gt;, and it&amp;rsquo;s difficult to do it precisely enough to determine the Sun&amp;rsquo;s changing mass.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is a much better way to measure the position of planets. Simply put a spacecraft in orbit around it. When the Cassini spacecraft was placed in orbit around Saturn, astronomers used radio signals from Cassini to measure the position of Saturn &lt;a href=&#34;https://briankoberlein.com/2015/01/13/last-mile/&#34;&gt;accurate to within a mile&lt;/a&gt;. We can do this because we know exactly what signal comes from the spacecraft, so any shift in that signal tells us how the spacecraft moves. When the Messenger spacecraft was placed in orbit, astronomers used the same technique to measure the position of Mercury. Using seven years of data they could also determine how Mercury&amp;rsquo;s motion changed over time. They did it precisely enough to observe the weakening of the Sun&amp;rsquo;s gravitational tug.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; They found that the Sun&amp;rsquo;s pull is weakening by about 0.4 trillionths of a percent per year. That agrees with estimates of the Sun&amp;rsquo;s mass loss due to core fusion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mercury has long been used as a test of Einstein&amp;rsquo;s theories. It&amp;rsquo;s motion was the &lt;a href=&#34;https://briankoberlein.com/2014/05/19/einstein-eddington/&#34;&gt;first confirmation&lt;/a&gt; that Einstein&amp;rsquo;s theory of gravity could be correct. It&amp;rsquo;s only fitting that Mercury has now be used to confirm &lt;a href=&#34;https://briankoberlein.com/2015/05/08/heart-of-the-matter/&#34;&gt;Einstein&amp;rsquo;s most famous equation&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;footnotes&#34;&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:1&#34;&gt;Genova, Antonio, et al. &amp;ldquo;Solar system expansion and strong equivalence principle as seen by the NASA MESSENGER mission.&amp;rdquo; Nature communications 9.1 (2018): 289. doi:&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.nature.com/articles/s41467-017-02558-1&#34;&gt;10.1038/s41467-017-02558-1&lt;/a&gt;
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:1&#34;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Back of the Envelope</title>
      <link>/back-of-the-envelope/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Sep 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/back-of-the-envelope/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Astrophysics (like any science) is about getting the details right. As I’ve mentioned earlier, the difference between two theoretical models can be very small (look at the &lt;a href=&#34;https://blog.briankoberlein.com/span-of-a-heartbeat/&#34;&gt;precession of Mercury&lt;/a&gt; as a case in point). But there are times when you just do a rough calculation to see if you are on the right track.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure class=&#34;right&#34;&gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;/image/pressure.png&#34; alt=&#34;Pressure for an ideal star.&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;
        Pressure for an ideal star.
        
            
        
        &lt;/p&gt; 
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Suppose you wanted to determine the pressure and temperature inside the Sun. We could start with a very simple model: assume the Sun is an ideal gas, sitting there quietly under its own weight (known as hydrostatic equilibrium). You would think this is a horrible approximation. The Sun is nothing like an ideal gas, right? It certainly isn’t static. It has flares and convection and is fusing elements in its core. Still, let’s see what our simple model predicts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the figures here I’ve graphed the pressure and temperature of the Sun as a function of its radius. All I’ve assumed is that I have a mass of ideal gas equal to the mass of the Sun, held together by its own weight. In astrophysics lingo, this model is one example of what’s known as a polytropic star. The exact shape of the graphs depends on the type of ideal gas you choose, so for these graphs I chose a gas that’s 75% hydrogen and 25% helium, which is roughly the percentages of the Sun.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure class=&#34;left&#34;&gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;/image/temperature.png&#34; alt=&#34;Temperature for an ideal star.&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;
        Temperature for an ideal star.
        
            
        
        &lt;/p&gt; 
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The result is that we calculate a central pressure of about 2,500 gigapascal, and a central temperature of about 3.5 million Kelvin. Compared to accepted values, our pressure is too low by a factor of about 100, and our temperature too low by about a factor of 5. Not too bad for such a rough approximation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That said, even our rough calculation tells us something important. At the pressure and temperature we calculated it is possible for fusion to occur. Our back of the envelope calculation tells us that we should expect the core of our sun to undergo fusion. When this model was first calculated, it was a good first step to understanding what powers the Sun, and it pointed us in the right direction to develop better models.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sometimes even a simplistic model can be very useful.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>