<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Website on Brian Koberlein</title>
    <link>/tags/website/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Website on Brian Koberlein</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <copyright>CC BY-NC 4.0</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 30 Aug 2013 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
        <atom:link href="/tags/website/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Small Beginnings</title>
      <link>/small-beginnings/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 30 Aug 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/small-beginnings/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;So I’ve finally made a personal website.  All the cool kids are doing it these days, and I didn’t want to be left behind.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve had personal websites before, but these have always been hosted by the various institutes where I’ve been employed, and over time these sites either relocated or faded away.  This is the first time I have a site with a domain and server I control, so I can ensure that pages won’t disappear, and the site won’t be relocated to another domain.  Here I stand, as it were.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some of you (perhaps most of you) may know that at the moment I spend most of my social media time on Google+, where &lt;a href=&#34;https://plus.google.com/+BrianKoberlein&#34;&gt;I write a great deal about astrophysics&lt;/a&gt;. That isn’t likely to change any time soon.  Google+ has a vibrant science community, and I will continue to write about astro-topics there primarily, or at least first.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But despite all the benefits of Google+, it is just one corner of the internet.  It is a rich garden, but a walled one.  So the initial goal of this site will be to move beyond the garden wall.  It will start small, and I’ll initially have posts about astronomy and astrophysics, since that’s what I’m most familiar with.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then we’ll just see where it goes.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>