<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Stars on Brian Koberlein</title>
    <link>/tags/stars/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Stars on Brian Koberlein</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <copyright>CC BY-NC 4.0</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 10 Apr 2018 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
        <atom:link href="/tags/stars/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>The Invisible Star</title>
      <link>/the-invisible-star/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Apr 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/the-invisible-star/</guid>
      <description><figure class="featured">
      <img src="/image/distantstar.png" alt="" />
      <figcaption><p>A distant star is magnified by the effects of gravitational lensing. Credit: NASA, ESA, and P. Kelly (University of Minnesota)</p></figcaption>
    </figure>&lt;p&gt;There&amp;rsquo;s a limit to how far into the cosmos we can see. One of the biggest limiting factors is simply the brightness of an object. The more distant an object, the dimmer the object will appear. Even if there is no gas or dust in the way, the brightness decreases proportional to the square of its distance. For example, if two stars are equally bright, and one is twice as far away as the other, we will observe four times the light from the closer star than we see from the distant star. Because of this, main sequence stars such as our Sun can only be observed out to a few hundred million light years. Galaxies can be seen from billions of light years away, as can brilliant supernovae, but not a simple star.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But sometimes fortune favors the fortunate. There is a way that gravity can make an object appear brighter than it actually is. Just as a telescope can magnify light of a distant object, so can a &lt;a href=&#34;https://briankoberlein.com/2013/09/09/gravitational-lensing/&#34;&gt;gravitational lens&lt;/a&gt;. Gravitational lensing occurs when light from a distant is deflected by the presence of mass along our line of sight. It was &lt;a href=&#34;https://briankoberlein.com/2014/05/19/einstein-eddington/&#34;&gt;first observed by Arthur Eddington&lt;/a&gt; in 1919, and was the first validation of general relativity. As light is deflected around a galaxy or other mass, we see it coming from multiple directions. This means more light reaches us than normally would without lensing. So the star looks brighter than we&amp;rsquo;d expect.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure class=&#34;right&#34;&gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;/image/gravitationallens.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;A schematic example of gravitational lensing.&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;
        A schematic example of gravitational lensing.
        
            
        
        &lt;/p&gt; 
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This particular star, informally known as Icarus, is behind a large cluster of galaxies &lt;a href=&#34;https://blog.briankoberlein.com/whats-name/&#34;&gt;called&lt;/a&gt; MACS J1149+2223, and while the mass of the cluster brightened the star a bit, it wasn&amp;rsquo;t enough to be easily seen by the Hubble Space Telescope. But then a star from the cluster happened to pass in front of the distant star. This created an effect known as an Einstein ring, where light from Icarus grazes the closer star and is focused in our direction. The result is a significant brightening of the star. The combination of gravitational lensing from the galaxy cluster and the Einstein ring made Icarus appear 2000 times brighter than it actually is, making it bright enough for Hubble to capture. It&amp;rsquo;s light traveled for 9 billion years to reach us, making it the most distant main sequence star we&amp;rsquo;ve ever observed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sadly, Icarus itself is long dead. Analysis of the light shows that Icarus was a blue supergiant, similar to the bright star Rigel in the constellation of Orion. These stars can be 10,000 times brighter than our Sun, but their brilliance comes at a cost. They typically only shine for a few million years before dying as a brilliant supernova. The flicker of Icarus captured by Hubble is a luminous echo of a star that died when the universe was only 4 billion years old. Long before our own Sun began to form.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Waking the Dead</title>
      <link>/waking-dead/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 07 Mar 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/waking-dead/</guid>
      <description><figure class="featured">
      <img src="/image/redgiantbinary.png" alt="" />
      <figcaption><p>An artist&#39;s rendering of a red giant and its neutron star companion. Credit: ESA</p></figcaption>
    </figure>&lt;p&gt;Every star dies. Our Sun will shine for about 5 billion more years, but the time will come when it swells to a red giant for a time, then collapse to become a white dwarf. Larger stars live shorter lives, and can eventually collapse to become neutron stars.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;White dwarfs and neutron stars can truly be considered dead stars. Unlike regular stars, they don&amp;rsquo;t generate heat internally through nuclear fusion. They don&amp;rsquo;t have active periods with solar flares. They simply cool slowly over billions of years.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure class=&#34;right&#34;&gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;/image/NSandMH.gif&#34; alt=&#34;A neutron star compared in size to Manhattan island.&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;
        A neutron star compared in size to Manhattan island.
        
            
        
        &lt;/p&gt; 
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;That is, unless they have a companion star. When two stars orbit each other closely, material from one star can sometimes transfer to the other. This most often occurs when a red giant and white dwarf orbit closely. Material from the outer layers of the red giant can captured by the white dwarf. If the white dwarf captures enough material, it can cause the white dwarf to collapse, triggering a supernova. In principle a similar effect should be possible with a neutron star, where material captured from a red dwarf companion causes the neutron star to be active again. Now this effect has been observed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As described in a paper&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; from Astronomy &amp;amp; Astrophysics, the team observed x-rays emitting from a previously quiet neutron star. The x-rays are generated when the neutron star captures matter from its companion. While this type of interaction isn&amp;rsquo;t surprising, it demonstrates how dynamic these binary systems can be, and it may help us better understand how these &amp;ldquo;odd-couple&amp;rdquo; binaries evolve over time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;footnotes&#34;&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:1&#34;&gt;Bozzo, E., et al. &amp;ldquo;IGR J17329-2731: The birth of a symbiotic X-ray binary.&amp;rdquo; arXiv preprint arXiv:1803.01593 (2018). &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1051/0004-6361/201832588&#34;&gt;DOI: 10.1051&amp;#47;0004-6361&amp;#47;201832588&lt;/a&gt;.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:1&#34;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Perception of Depth</title>
      <link>/perception-of-depth/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 31 Aug 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/perception-of-depth/</guid>
      <description><figure class="featured">
      <img src="/image/brightstar.jpg" alt="" />
      <figcaption><p>Twinkle twinkle, little star. I know how far away you are.</p></figcaption>
    </figure>&lt;p&gt;If you’ve ever watched a 3D movie, you’ve noticed how the image on the screen appears to have a certain depth to it. Certain objects just seem farther away. Other objects (usually pointy things) seem to leap out from the screen. You’ve also probably noticed that you have to wear a pair of glasses to watch the movie. If you take the glasses off during the movie, things look somewhat blurry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;3D movies work by projecting two movies at the same time. The two movies are almost identical, except that one was filmed (or computer generated) slightly to the left of center, and the other was filmed slightly to the right. This means that each movie has a slightly different point of view. The movies are projected on a special screen such that the light reflected from right projector is polarized one way, and the light from the left projector is polarized another. The glasses you wear are polarizing filters, and they ensure that only the left image reaches your left eye and only the right image reaches your right eye. With the glasses on, you see a different point of view in each eye. When you take the glasses off, you see both images at once, which is why they look blurry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This trick works because (most) humans have depth perception. Our brains are able to integrate these two points of view into a perception of near and far. The same effect exists in the real world, and helps us do things like catch baseballs (or duck for the less athletically inclined). But the effect is typically more dramatic in the theater.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Depth perception is possible because a closer object exhibits a parallax shift when compared to more distant object. You can see this effect by looking at a a distant object. Close one eye, and hold up your thumb to cover the distant object. Without moving your thumb, switch eyes. What you will see is that your thumb has shifted because of the different point of view. If you hold your thumb closer to your face you get a bigger shift. Farther away and you get a smaller shift. This relationship is true in general. The closer the object the bigger the parallax shift. So by observing the parallax of objects, your brain can gauge their distance.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure class=&#34;right&#34;&gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;/image/parallax.gif&#34; alt=&#34;An example of parallax. Credit: University of Virginia&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;
        An example of parallax. Credit: University of Virginia
        
            
        
        &lt;/p&gt; 
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;We can use the same effect to measure the distances of stars, using the width of Earth’s orbit. As the Earth moves around the Sun, you can measure the apparent position of a star against more distant stars. Over time you can observe the shift when the Earth is at one side of its orbit, and when its at the other side. That gives us two points of view separated by about 186 million miles (the actual distance varies depending on direction of the star in relation to Earth). This seems like a huge distance to us, but the parallax shift of stars is very small. Even the closest stars (not counting the Sun) are about 1 parsec away (a bit less than 4 light-years), which means they have a parallax shift of about 1 second of arc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’ve been able to use this cosmic depth perception to measure stellar distances up to about 1500 light years. Beyond that and the parallax shift is too small to measure accurately. Of course that raises the question of how we measure distances of farther objects. How can we say something is millions of light years away, or billions? For that we need several other methods, which together are known as the cosmic distance ladder.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But that’s a story for another time.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>